{"tossups": [{"question": "The men's section of this event was dominated by Bill Rodgers in the 1970s. In 1980, Rosie Ruiz was disqualified from this event after initially \"winning\" its women's title by taking shortcuts. From 2002 to 2013, all men's winners of this event were from either Kenya or Ethiopia. For 10 points, name this distance running event which, in 2013, was attacked by terrorists.", "answer": "<b><u>Boston Marathon</u></b> [or <b><u>New York Marathon</u></b> until \"Rosie Ruiz\" is read]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man's fictitious sister Judith is hypothesized to make a point about women writers in Virginia Woolf's <em>A Room of One's Own</em>. This man left only his \"second-best bed\" to his widow Anne Hathaway, but did leave women such roles as Cordelia, Beatrice, and Ophelia. For 10 points, name this author of <em>King Lear</em>, <em>Much Ado About Nothing</em>, and <em>Hamlet.</em>", "answer": "William <b><u>Shakespeare</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Schoolgirl Venetia Burney proposed what is now the official name of this object. This body was discovered in 1930 using the blink comparator machine by Vesto Slipher's new apprentice, Clyde Tombaugh. In 2006, this object was demoted by the International Astronomical Union to \"dwarf planet\" status. For 10 points, name this trans-Neptunian object and former ninth planet.", "answer": "<b><u>Pluto</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "Peter Shann Ford has attempted to prove, using acoustic analysis, that this man did not flub a line that had been scripted for him. This man indicated that \"the Eagle has landed\" while on a mission with Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin. For 10 points, name this commander of <em>Apollo</em> <em>11</em> who said \"one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind\" as he took the first step onto the Moon.", "answer": "Neil <b><u>Armstrong</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "According to this religion, a compass-like device called the Liahona (<b>pr. LEE-uh-HOH-nuh</b>) was used to show an escape route from Jerusalem. Other artifacts of this religion include Urim and Thummim, the \"seer stones\" used to translate the golden plates which the angel Moroni revealed to its founder. For 10 points, name this church founded by Joseph Smith.", "answer": "<b><u>Mormon</u></b> church [or <b><u>LDS</u></b>; or Church of Jesus Christ of <b><u>Latter-Day Saints</u></b>]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This city once turned away foreign help during an earthquake in fear of contaminating its social system, which involved events such as the \"krypteia\" (<b>pr. crip-TAY-uh</b>), a ritual declaration of war on its slave class, the helots (<b>pr. HELL-ots</b>). For 10 points, name this city where two lines of kings oversaw the cultivation of boys from age seven into full-time soldiers.", "answer": "<b><u>Sparta</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Council of Trent mandated that Catholic realms adopt this standard, which did not arrive in Greece until 1923. It replaced an earlier standard named for Julius Caesar. When it was introduced to Great Britain in 1751, monthly debtors cried \"give us back our eleven days.\" For 10 points, identify this modern calendar named for the Pope who devised it.", "answer": "<b><u>Gregorian</u></b> calendar", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "American \"shows\" described by this word featured stock characters such as Mr. Bones and performers dressed in blackface. In the middle ages, this word generally described people such as minnesingers (<b>pr. MIN-eh-singers</b>) and troubadours, who sang or played the harp, flute, or lute. For 10 points, name these people who were travelling musicians of the middle ages.", "answer": "<b><u>minstrel</u></b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Southern supporters of this man launched racist attacks on his opponent by claiming that this man's rival danced with Mary Booze. This man became president of the firm constructing the Empire State Building after losing the 1928 Presidential election to Herbert Hoover. For 10  points,  name  this  \"Happy  Warrior,\"  the  first  major-party  Catholic  candidate.", "answer": "Al <b><u>Smith</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person was appointed as the head of an expedition to Scutari (<b>pr. scoo-TAH-ree</b>) by war minister Sidney Herbert, who knew of her efforts to improve sanitation. She became known as the \"Lady with the Lamp\" for her efforts during the Crimean War. For 10 points, name this 1850s British woman, the founder of modern nursing.", "answer": "Florence <b><u>Nightingale</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Shortly after his death, this man was nominated for an Oscar for his work on <em>Shall We Dance</em>, for which he wrote the song \"They Can't Take That Away From Me\" with his brother Ira. This composer used traffic horns in the score to <em>An American in Paris</em> and rumbas in his <em>Cuban</em> <em>Overture</em>. For 10 points, name this composer of the jazz concerto <em>Rhapsody in Blue.</em>", "answer": "George <b><u>Gershwin</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The Bally and Williams corporations grew by manufacturing units for this game. Montague Redgrave patented the spring launcher central to this game in 1871, and in 1950, David Gottlieb created its modern form by adjusting the position of the controllable flippers. For 10 points, identify this arcade game, in which points are scored for keeping the metal balls in play.", "answer": "<b><u>pinball</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "In this African country, the Orange Democratic Movement arose following political fragmentation when Daniel arap Moi retired. This country's independence came shortly after General China led the Mau Mau Rebellion against British rule here. For 10 points, name this country where the Leakey family's research on human origins took place at Olduvai Gorge.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Kenya</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This party effectively ceased to function after the failure of Rufus King's Presidential campaign. They were discredited when members were accused of using blue lights to signal to British ships during the War of 1812, and by their organization of the secessionist Hartford Convention. For 10 points, name this party of DeWitt Clinton, Alexander Hamilton, and John Adams.", "answer": "<b><u>Federalist</u></b> Party [or the <b><u>Federalist</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Popes from this family presided over the Council of Trent and the start of the Protestant Reformation. This family of Leo X and Pius IV was targeted by the Pazzi (<b>pr. POT-see</b>) Conspiracy and first rose to power in Tuscany under the banker Cosimo. For 10 points, identify this political family which ruled Florence through such members as Lorenzo the Magnificent.", "answer": "de <b><u>Medici</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man discussed the fall of the First Republic in his \"Cartagena (<b>pr. cart-uh-HAY-nuh</b>) Manifesto.\" This man conquered New Granada with his lieutenant, Francisco Santander, and accepted a Spanish surrender at Boyac\u00e1 (<b>pr. boy-uh-CAH</b>). For 10 points, name this \"libertador\" who was the icon of South American independence in Colombia and Venezuela.", "answer": "Sim\u00f3n <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This city built the luxurious Segovia Bridge over the unimpressive Manzanares (<b>pr. mon-zuh-NAH-race</b>) River. This home of the Queen Sofia Museum became capital in 1560, replacing Toledo. The palace El Escorial (<b>pr. ess-core-ee-AHL</b>) is found just outside this city, which is the home of the Prado art museum. For 10 points, name this capital of Spain.", "answer": "<b><u>Madrid</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The informer \"Stakeknife\" infiltrated this organization, which began the \"Long War\" in the early 1970s. This group claimed responsibility for killing MP Airey Neave as well as the 1984 Brighton hotel bombing which nearly killed Margaret Thatcher. For 10 points, name this militant Catholic group which advocated transferring Northern Ireland away from the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b><u>IRA</u></b> [<b><u>Irish Republican Army</u></b>] [or Provisional <b><u>IRA</u></b>; or Provisional <b><u>Irish</u></b> <b><u>Republican Army</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>During primaries for this year's election, a candidate won applause in a high school</u></b> <b><u>gymnasium after yelling \"I am paying for this microphone!\" Another party's primaries in</u></b> <b><u>this election year featured a strong challenge to the incumbent from (+)</u> Ted Kennedy. This election also included independent candidate John Anderson</b>. (*) For 10 points, identify this election year which resulted in the end of Jimmy Carter's Presidency and the start of the Ronald Reagan administration.", "answer": "United States Presidential election of <b><u>1980</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This Supreme Court case was analogous to the</u> </b><em><b><u>Sweatt v. Painter</u> </b></em><b><u>decision which came</u></b> <b><u>down four years earlier. The ruling in this Supreme Court case drew on Kenneth and</u></b> <b><u>Mamie Clark's (+)</u> doll experiments. A followup to this case ordered its ruling implemented \"with all deliberate speed.\" Thurgood (*)</b> Marshall successfully argued this case on behalf of the NAACP. For 10 points, name this unanimous 1954 ruling of the Warren court against segregated public schools.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Brown</u></b> v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas</em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Kicking Bear adapted a Mormon belief into an auxiliary practice of this movement, in</u></b> <b><u>which bullet-repelling shirts were worn. This movement's main ritual was adapted from</u></b> <b><u>earlier \"circle\" performances by (+)</u> Wodziwob, and it spread across the Plains under the leadership of (*) </b>Wovoka, who preached that it would end white encroachment on Indian lands. For 10 points, name this Indian religious movement whose practitioners were massacred in 1890 at Wounded Knee.", "answer": "<b><u>Ghost Dance</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>To show that the Federal Reserve's contractionary economic policy exacerbated the</u></b> <b><u>Great Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on</u> </b><em><b><u>A</u> </b></em><b><u>(+)</u></b><em><b> Monetary History of </b><b>the United States</b></em><b>. He popularized his ideas on the relationship between the free market and individual liberty in the PBS miniseries </b><em><b>Free to Choose</b></em><b>. (*)</b> For 10 points, name this leader of the Chicago school of economics who founded monetarism.", "answer": "Milton <b><u>Friedman</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man became President by defeating former Civil War general Benjamin Butler of</u></b> <b><u>the Greenback Party and Prohibition candidate John St. John. He edged out his major-</u><u>party opponent with a last-minute swing of the (+)</u> New York vote, triggered by Samuel Burchard denouncing him as the candidate of (*)</b> \"rum, Romanism, and rebellion.\" For 10 points, name this first post-Civil War Democrat to win the Presidency, who served nonconsecutive terms.", "answer": "Grover <b><u>Cleveland</u></b> [Stephen Grover <b><u>Cleveland</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This organization had a major political effect in 1996, after its weapons master Yahya</u></b> <b><u>Ayyash was killed and it launched a wave of bus bombings. This organization designates its</u></b> <b><u>armed wing the (+)</u> Izzedine al-Qassam (</b>pr. EYE zuh-DEEN ah-kah-SEM<b>) Brigades, and it gained popularity by resisting the (*) </b>Oslo Accords. For 10 points, name this Islamist group which opposes the existence of Israel and controls the Gaza Strip.", "answer": "<b><u>Hamas</u></b> [<b><u>Harakat Al-Muqawama Al-Islamia</u></b>] [or <b><u>Islamic Resistance Movement</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Julius von Sachs identified the organelles in which this process takes place. The</u></b> <b><u>experiments of Jan Ingenhousz (</u></b><u>pr. ING-en-hoos</u><b><u>) showed that this process altered the mass</u></b> <b><u>of the (+)</u> organisms involved. Joseph Priestley performed an experiment involving a candle and (*)</b> mint that showed that this process changes the composition of air. For 10 points, identify this process of plants using light to create sugars from carbon dioxide.", "answer": "<b><u>photosynthesis</u></b> [or the <b><u>Calvin cycle</u></b>]", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b><u>This emperor was the ultimate victor of the Battle of Muhlberg, which suppressed the</u></b> <b><u>Schmalkaldic (</u></b><u>pr. shmal-CALL-dik</u><b><u>) League that opposed him. This man's 1525 victory at</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Pavia included the capture of Francis I of France. This father of Philip II summoned (*</b>) Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms (<b>pr. VURMZ</b>). For 10 points, name this Hapsburg who briefly united the thrones of Spain and the Holy Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles V</u></b> [or <b><u>Charles I</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Charles</u></b>]  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 7 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras </b> <b><u>These people were sought out due to the new doctrine of \"limpieza de sangre\" (</u></b><u>pr.leem-pee-EY-zuh day SAHN-gray</u><b><u>), or \"cleanliness of blood.\" These people were given a</u></b> <b><u>derogatory nickname meaning (+)</u> \"pig\" and were subject to the public \"auto de fe\" (</b>pr. OW-toe deh FAY<b>) if found. Tomas de Torquemada gave these people three months to leave (*)</b> Spain in 1492. For 10 points, name these people whom the Inquisition sought to find survivals of within the \"conversos\" community.  ANSWER: Spanish former <b><u>Jew</u></b>s [or secret <b><u>Jew</u></b>s, etc.]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}